At this point we have seen that
the critical section problem can
be solved in several different
ways. We are going to look into
one more solution which has some extra nice
property: the Lamport's Bakery algorithm.
Lamport is one of the recipients of the Turing
award and came up with the following idea.
Simply put: all the threads who want to enter a
critical section need to get a number. The thread
with the smallest number is the one that can
enter. Imagine a take-a-number system, basically.
We assume the numbers given by the
take-a-number system are non-decreasing.
Non-decreasing means that two or more
consecutive numbers can be the same.
If we also assume each thread has a unique
id, we can break ties saying that if two or
more threads have the same number, the one with
the smallest id can enter its critical section.
Let's look at the complete example.
We have two shared arrays each with n
elements (n is the number of threads).
The first array, choosing, contains
booleans initialized to false.
The second array, number,
contains integers initialized to 0.
In its entry section, thread i starts
by setting true to its entry in choosing.
Then, it computes the max value for all entries in
number plus 1 and stores it in its number entry.
Finally, it sets false to its entry in choosing.
Then, it does a complete pass over the
n entries of the arrays, but it spins on
each entry j if such an entry is choosing or if
such an entry has a lower number,j combination
but the number is not 0 (number,j combination
because we use threads' ids to break ties).
Then it enters the section.
Once the critical section is over,
the thread simply sets its number back to 0.
Before discussing why this solution is valid,
please notice that each thread is only
modifying its own entry in the array.
I ask you to formally reason
about why this solution is valid,
I am only doing a rapid discussion. For mutual
exclusion, you can conclude that if a thread
enters its critical section, then that thread
is sure no other thread has a lower number.
When the thread is in, can another thread obtain
a lower number and enter the critical section?
No, beacuse the number is always
the max of all threads + 1,
so it will be at least +1 compared to the
thread that is running its critical section.
When it comes to progress, the thread with
the smallest number can always proceed.
When it comes to fairness, notice that once a
thread starts waiting and another enters its
critical section, the next number the latter will
get is higher than that of the waiting thread.
Now going back to what I said in the beginning,
about the nice property of this algorithm,
is that it works also with primitives that
are weaker than atomic read/write. In fact,
this is one of the algorithms that gave rise
to research in lock-free synchronization.